<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright (c) 2024 Coalition for Health AI, Inc.

The license for this source code can be found at https://mc.chai.org/LICENSE.
-->
<AppliedModelCard
	xmlns="https://mc.chai.org/v0.1/schema.xsd"
	xmlns:bibtex="http://bibtexml.sf.net/">
	<BasicInfo>
		<ModelName>BriefCase-Quantification of Midline Shift (MLS)</ModelName>
		<ModelDeveloper>Aidoc</ModelDeveloper>
		<DeveloperContact>www.aidoc.com/contact-support/ or email:info@aidoc.com</DeveloperContact>
	</BasicInfo>
	<ReleaseInfo>
		<ReleaseStage>FDA Cleared, Commercial (K232083)</ReleaseStage>
		<ReleaseDate>November 2023</ReleaseDate>
		<ReleaseVersion>MLS-01</ReleaseVersion>
		<GlobalAvailability>US, EU (CE Marked), UK (UKCA Marked), Canada (MDEL), Israel (AMAR), UAE and South Africa.</GlobalAvailability>
		<RegulatoryApproval>Please find attached the MLS-01 [510(k) summary](https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfpmn/pmn.cfm?ID=K232083).</RegulatoryApproval>
	</ReleaseInfo>
	<ModelSummary>
		<Summary>Brief Case-Quantification of Midline Shift (MLS) is a radiological image management and processing system software intended for automatic measurement of brain midline shift in non-contrast head CT (NCCT) images, in adults or transitional adolescents aged 18 years and older. The device is intended to assist appropriately trained medical specialists by providing the user with an automated current manual process of measuring midline shift. The device provides midline shift measurement from NCCT images acquired at a single time point, and can additionally provide an output with comparative analysis of two or more images that were acquired in the same individual at multiple time points. The device does not alter the original medical image and is not intended to be used as a diagnostic device. The BriefCase-Quantification results are not intended to be used on a stand-alone basis for clinical decision-making or otherwise preclude clinical assessment of cases. Clinicians are responsible for viewing full images per the standard of care.</Summary>
		<Keywords />
	</ModelSummary>
	<UsesAndDirections>
		<IntendedUseAndWorkflow>The Brief Case-Quantification of Midline Shift (MLS) is a radiological image management and processing system software intended for automatic measurement of brain midline shift in non-contrast head CT (NCCT) images, in adults or transitional adolescents aged 18 years and older. The device is intended to assist appropriately trained medical specialists by providing the user with an automated current manual process of measuring midline shift.</IntendedUseAndWorkflow>
		<PrimaryIntendedUsers>Brief Case-Quantification of Midline Shift is intended to be used by appropriately trained medical specialists. Appropriately trained medical specialists for midline shift measurement include radiologists, emergency physicians, surgeons, interventionalists, and neurologists.</PrimaryIntendedUsers>
		<HowToUse>BriefCase-Quantification of Midline Shift (MLS) is a radiological image management and processing system software intended for automatic measurement of brain midline shift in non-contrast head CT (NCCT) images, in adults or transitional adolescents aged 18 years and older. The device is intended to assist appropriately trained medical specialists by providing the user with an automated current manual process of measuring midline shift. The device provides midline shift measurement from NCCT images acquired at a single time point, and can additionally provide an output with comparative analysis of two or more images that were acquired in the same individual at multiple time points</HowToUse>
		<TargetedPatientPopulation>Adults or transitional adolescents aged 18 and older.</TargetedPatientPopulation>
		<CautionedOutOfScopeSettings>results are not intended to be used on a stand-alone basis for clinical decision-making or otherwise preclude clinical assessment of cases. These measurements are unofficial, are not final, and are subject to change after review by a radiologist. For final clinically approved measurements, please refer to the official radiology report. Clinicians are responsible for viewing full images per the standard of care. Only for use by appropriately trained medical specialists. Please refer to BriefCase-Quantification User Guide (UG0010) for further information on warnings and precautions.</CautionedOutOfScopeSettings>
	</UsesAndDirections>
	<Warnings>
		<KnownRisksAndLimitations>Notified clinicians are responsible for viewing full images per the standard of care. Please refer to BriefCase-Quantification User Guide ([UG0010](https://community.aidoc.com/private/login)), label, and additional tutorial materials provided by the company for further information on risks and limitations.</KnownRisksAndLimitations>
		<KnownBiasesOrEthicalConsiderations>None</KnownBiasesOrEthicalConsiderations>
		<ClinicalRiskLevel>Low, Class II (FDA) / IIa (EU)</ClinicalRiskLevel>
	</Warnings>
	<TrustIngredients>
		<AISystemFacts>
			<OutcomesAndOutputs>The device provides midline shift measurement from NCCT images acquired at a single time point, and can additionally provide an output with comparative analysis of two or more images that were acquired in the same individual at multiple time points.</OutcomesAndOutputs>
			<ModelType>Custom-built 3D deep convolutional neural network.</ModelType>
			<InputDataSource>The BriefCase-Quantification imaging AI solutions are trained, tuned, and validated using diverse data sets. Specifically, Aidoc works with DICOM images, which capture anatomical and physiological data from medical imaging technologies like CT scans and X-rays. These data sets are sourced from a wide range of institutions, including community hospitals, academic centers, teleradiology providers, private clinics, and imaging centers across various global regions (e.g., east and west US, central US, EU, and other parts of the world).</InputDataSource>
			<OutputAndInputDataTypes>Input: Real World Digital imaging and communications in medicine (DICOM) images.

Inclusion criteria: Non-contrast head CT images. Scans performed on adults/transitional adults ≥ 18 years of age. Slice thickness: 0.625 mm - 5.0 mm axial slices

Exclusion Criteria: Delayed contrast studies

Output: A Summary report with measurement information of midline shift and annotated images.</OutputAndInputDataTypes>
			<DevelopmentDataCharacterization>The Midline Shift model has been trained, tuned, and validated on over 45,000 scans. The training and validation populations consist of a wide range of institutions and patient settings, including academic centers, community hospitals, teleradiology providers, private imaging centers, and clinics worldwide (specifically East, West, and Center of US, EU, Middle East, Oceania, Latin America and far east).

Analyzed data included key demographic elements such as age, gender, comorbidities, geographical location, patient settings, reason for exam, and technological characteristics (e.g., equipment manufacturer, slice thickness, and modality model distribution).

The time frame for the data used for the initial and retrained model construction and validation is 2019-2022.</DevelopmentDataCharacterization>
			<BiasMitigationApproaches>Aidoc's AI solutions undergo rigorous training, validation, and monitoring to ensure robust and equitable performance across diverse patient populations. Bias mitigation and advancing care equity are highly prioritized throughout the design and development of Aidoc solutions, while working within the known constraints of limited accessibility to certain data elements.

Recognizing these constraints, Aidoc creates proxies to effectively mitigate risks associated with the absence of certain demographic details, when applicable.

Specifically, race, ethnicity, language, sexual orientation, gender identity, social determinants of health data, and health status assessment data are not accessible as part of the DICOM image.

To address potential biases, Aidoc employs diverse data sets from a wide range of institutions and patient settings, including academic centers, community hospitals, teleradiology providers, private imaging centers, and clinics worldwide (specifically East, West, and Center of US, EU, Middle East, Oceania, Latin America and far east).

Aidoc validates and measures the AI model across subpopulations to ensure a normal and predictable performance on them. Additionally, key demographic elements are analyzed such as age, gender, comorbidities, geographical location, patient settings, reason for exam, and technological characteristics (e.g., equipment manufacturer, slice thickness, and modality model distribution);

Furthermore, Aidoc conducts multiple retraining throughout the lifecycle of each AI module to ensure increased generalizability across all the aforementioned parameters. While the exact size of Aidoc's training data sets is proprietary, over the model lifecycle, they may include up to millions of DICOM studies.</BiasMitigationApproaches>
			<OngoingMaintenance>Aidoc's quality management system is ISO 13485 MDSAP and EU MDR certified, and 21 CFR Part 820 compliant, requiring structured and validated installation, servicing, and Post-Market Surveillance (PMS) activities.

Specifically, Aidoc's PMS plan outlines the systematic collection and analysis of data regarding the device's safety and performance throughout its lifecycle.

Data analysis methods, both qualitative and quantitative, are applied to the collected data. The results are documented in a PMS report and in a Periodic Safety Update Report (PSUR). In addition, Aidoc implements site-specific controls, ensuring high standards are consistently maintained across all operational locations. The current Midline Shift model represents the first FDA clearance for Midline Shift at Aidoc. Aidoc periodically retrains the algorithm on additional data and subjects the retrained versions to the required regulatory review and controls.

An expanded dataset enhances the model's generalization capabilities and potentially elevates the product's performance (improved or non-inferior to the previously cleared device's Time-to-Notification and/or AUC). The inclusion of data from a broader and more diverse array of sources enhances the model's ability to perform effectively across a wider range of clinical and technical settings, particularly if any real-world data changes or if any data was underrepresented in the original dataset.

**Continuous monitoring**: As detailed in the previous answer, Aidoc has robust monitoring systems in place to track the AI performance and identify any emerging issues, such as AI drift. In addition, regular audits and assessments ensure the model continues to deliver fair and accurate prioritizations.

Furthermore, Aidoc remains committed to ongoing research and development to refine the AI and address any safety concerns that may arise. The Aidoc AI Monitoring team monitors algorithm performance 24/7 for the purpose of mitigating AI drift. The team monitors and considers aspects such as alert correctness, the timeliness of data available, data completeness, slice thickness, series correctness and relevancy, contrast phase, algorithm specificity, and algorithmic positive ratio.</OngoingMaintenance>
			<Security>Aidoc's products are structured based on international quality, privacy, and security standards and frameworks, including ISO 13485, ISO 27001, ISO 27017, ISO 27018, ISO 27799, SOC 2 Type 2, Cyber Essentials, and C5. Aidoc follows a systematic approach, integrating these frameworks into Aidoc's Information Security Management System (ISMS) to ensure a holistic and proactive risk management strategy.

Aidoc's risk management program involves regular risk assessments, leveraging common methodologies, to identify, evaluate, and prioritize risks. Continuous monitoring, periodic audits, and assessments contribute to the dynamic nature of Aidoc's risk management program, allowing us to adapt to evolving threats and vulnerabilities. Aidoc regularly monitors its server's logs for unusual activity and implements intrusion detection and prevention systems, paying attention to unusual or suspicious activities such as unexpected errors, system slowdowns, or strange user access patterns. Furthermore, Aidoc conducts multiple retraining throughout the lifecycle of each AI module.

Additionally, Aidoc's Governance, Risk, and Compliance (GRC) Program is responsible for enterprise oversight and direction for all security governance activities; governance for risk-related activities including Risk Identification, Management, Mitigation, and Remediation, and Risk Assessments; and responsibility for the planning, execution, and adherence with Aidoc Security Policies and Procedures, legal, regulatory, and contractual requirements.</Security>
			<Transparency>The company ensures Transparency, Intelligibility, and Accountability in Aidoc's medical devices via its product design and its Quality Management System (QMS). Some examples include (non-exhaustive list):
- Explainability and transparency features by design;
- Reporting and feedback mechanism directly via the device's UI and additional communication in different platforms;
- User guide, labeling, and additional tutorial materials are available electronically at all times via the user community;
- Robust user training.</Transparency>
		</AISystemFacts>
		<TransparencyInformation>
			<FundingSource>Aidoc's model creation is self-funded.</FundingSource>
			<StakeholdersConsulted>Physicians, health system administrators, and patient groups were engaged in the development of the model</StakeholdersConsulted>
		</TransparencyInformation>
	</TrustIngredients>
	<KeyMetrics>
		<UsefulnessUsabilityEfficacy>
			<MetricGoal>Evaluate the software's performance in providing adequate measurements of the midline shift in non-contrast head CT images in 284 cases from 228 unique patients from 6 US-based clinical sites</MetricGoal>
			<Result>The algorithm performance showed that the mean absolute error between the ground truth measurement and algorithm was 0.94 mm (95% CI: 0.74 mm, 1.14 mm) mm. Because the mean absolute error estimate is lower than the prespecified performance goal, the study's primary endpoint was achieved.</Result>
			<Interpretation>Primary endpoints were mean absolute error between the ground truth measurement and algorithm which was 0.94 mm (95% CI: 0.74 mm, 1.14 mm) mm. Because the mean absolute error estimate is lower than the prespecified performance goal, the study's primary endpoint was achieved.</Interpretation>
			<TestType>Retrospective, blinded, multicenter study.</TestType>
			<TestingDataDescription>The mean age of patients whose scans were reviewed for BriefCaseQuantification of Midline Shift (MLS) was 64.4 years, with a standard deviation of 20.1 years. Gender distribution was 48.3% male, and 48.8% female. Race distribution within the study data patient population was unavailable. None of the potential covariates demonstrated statistical significance, thus, device performance did not meaningfully interact with location, gender or age.</TestingDataDescription>
			<ValidationProcessAndJustification>Methods used are described in the [510(k) summary](https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/cdrh_docs/pdf23/K232083.pdf).</ValidationProcessAndJustification>
		</UsefulnessUsabilityEfficacy>
		<FairnessEquity>
			<MetricGoal>Evaluate for differences in performance (mean absolute error) based on available socio-demographic variables of age, location and gender.</MetricGoal>
			<Result>Same result as Usefulness, Usability, and Efficacy section.</Result>
			<Interpretation>Device performance did not meaningfully interact with location, gender or age (Race distribution for sample was unavailable).</Interpretation>
			<TestType>Retrospective, blinded, multicenter study</TestType>
			<TestingDataDescription>Same study as Usefulness, Usability, and Efficacy section.</TestingDataDescription>
			<ValidationProcessAndJustification>[Link to Methods Description](https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/cdrh_docs/pdf23/K232083.pdf)</ValidationProcessAndJustification>
		</FairnessEquity>
		<SafetyReliability>
			<MetricGoal>To show an agreement between the ground truth compared to the algorithm output.</MetricGoal>
			<Result>The mean age of patients whose scans were reviewed for BriefCaseQuantification of Midline Shift (MLS) was 64.4 years, with a standard deviation of 20.1 years. Gender distribution was 48.3% male, and 48.8% female</Result>
			<Interpretation>The mean difference between the two measurements was -0.15 mm, indicating that there is little to no bias between the two measurements, demonstrating the study's secondary endpoint was achieved. The mean absolute error in midline shift was 1.16 mm (95% CI: 0.61 mm, 1.71 mm) for the first case and 1.28 mm (95% CI: 0.68 mm, 1.88 mm) for the follow-up cases. Because the mean absolute error estimate is lower than the prespecified performance goal, the study's secondary endpoint was achieved.</Interpretation>
			<TestType>A Bland-Altman plot demonstrated an agreement between the ground truth compared to the algorithm output.</TestType>
			<TestingDataDescription>Same study as Usefulness, Usability, and Efficacy section.</TestingDataDescription>
			<ValidationProcessAndJustification>[Link to Methods Description](https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/cdrh_docs/pdf23/K232083.pdf)

AiDoc develops software within a Design Control process that is aligned with FDA 21 CFR Part 820 and ISO 62304 Medical device software - Software life cycle processes.</ValidationProcessAndJustification>
		</SafetyReliability>
	</KeyMetrics>
	<Resources>
		<EvaluationReferences>Please reference our clinical [compendium](https://www.aidoc.com/learn/ebooks-whitepapers/aidoc-clinical-compendium/).</EvaluationReferences>
		<PeerReviewedPublications>Aidoc's clinical compendium with 100+ Peer-reviewed publications or abstract/conference presentations are available at the following [link](https://www.aidoc.com/learn/ebooks-whitepapers/aidoc-clinical-compendium/).</PeerReviewedPublications>
		<PatientConsentOrDisclosure>N/A</PatientConsentOrDisclosure>
	</Resources>
	<Bibliography />
</AppliedModelCard>